Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, good חודש. chodesh. So we
are, today's דף daf is דף ל"ג daf lamed gimmel
and we pick up at the bottom of ל"ב עמוד ב'. lamed
beis amud beis.
Okay, and we are dealing with the משנה mishna that says that
if you've got a, if you put your עירוב eruv in a
tree, you know, some of this I gotta tell you reminds me
of the Dr. Seuss
book of, what is it, Green Eggs and Ham, would you eat
it in a box, right, because we were taking the box in
the בית הקברות, beis hakevaros, right, so would you eat it in
a tree. So okay, anyway, I think that would be a perfect,
it should be, we could make a, we could do a רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafos on the whole book.
Anyway, okay, so we have putting your עירוב eruv in the tree
and assuming the base of the tree is רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
and if it's, so it's higher than עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and
as we'll find out, if it's ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim by ארבעה
טפחים, arba tefachim, so the tree is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
so that's not good because you and the עירוב eruv are not
in the same place, you wouldn't be able to take the עירוב
eruv to where you are. And the use of a tree, although
that's also forbidden, that's rabbinic and this is going according to רבי
Rebbi that says rabbinic is not a problem בין השמשות bein hashmashos
and that's when the עירוב eruv takes effect. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, we are eight lines from the bottom, line
starts with השמשות. hashmashos. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, לא
שנו אלא באילן העומד חוץ לעיבורה
של עיר. lo shanu ella be-ilan ha-omed chutz le-ibura shel ir. This
is only if the tree is outside of the עיבורה של עיר,
ibura shel ir, literally the pregnancy of the city, meaning the sort
of like,
basically the הלכה halacha is the following is that you have a
city and as long as you have a house within 70 and
2/3 אמות, amos, it extends the outer edge of the city. So
70 and 2/3 אמות amos is considered to be continuous houses and
continuous parameters of the city, so 70 and 2/3 is considered the
עיבורה, ibura, the pregnancy of the city. Okay, we'll worry about that,
it's the square root of 5000 of a בית סאה beis se'ah
which we've seen before as being significant. Okay, so that's only if
this tree is outside of the עיבורה ibura of the city. Okay,
I'll read it and then I'll explain it. אבל אילן העומד בתוך
עיבורה של עיר, aval ilan ha-omed betoch ibura shel ir, if it's
within the pregnancy of the city, אפילו למעלה מעשרה הרי זה
עירוב, afilu lemala mi-asara harei zeh eruv, even higher than ten it
counts, דמתא כמאן דמליא דמיא, demasa keman demalya damya,
a city is like it is filled. Now you might remember from
the beginning of שבת, Shabbos, ביתא כמאן דמליא דמיא, beisa keman demalya
damya, a house is like it is filled. What does this mean?
So first I need to tell you the point that רש"י Rashi
says. If your עירוב eruv is within 70 and 2/3, right, if
here's the 70 and 2/3, he says who needs an עירוב? eruv?
Right? Because your city goes up to that limit. So what do
you mean if it's within 70 and 2/3? We are talking about
עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. We are talking about עירוב. eruv. So רש"י
Rashi says the case is is that this is your city, your
city is in A. It happens to be that your city is
in A, B
is within 2000 אמות. amos. So if you start in A, right,
you can go all the way till B and you can go
another hundred אמות amos outside of B. B is considered one place,
you know, like doesn't take up any space. Okay, that's if you
were to start your שבת Shabbos in A. But you actually wanted
to get all the way over here, right, so you wouldn't have
been able to do it if you started in A. So you
went ahead and you put your עירוב eruv over here in order
to allow you to get over there. And where's the case? So
that would be a scenario where you would need an עירוב eruv
within the 70 and 2/3. If you started in B, you don't
need an עירוב eruv because your city goes up to that limit.
Okay, but if you're starting in A, then you naturally you wouldn't
get as far, so therefore that's the case. So that's not so
relevant, just to explain why you'd need the עירוב eruv there. But
here's what רבא Rava is saying, is that if you have the
עירוב eruv within this limit, then even if it's in a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, right, here's your nice tree, it's ten טפחים, tefachim,
okay, and your עירוב eruv is here, okay, if this tree is
in the עיבורה של עיר, ibura shel ir, even though the street
is a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and even though technically the tree
is רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, because it's considered to be that you're
in the city, the city for the purposes of where you put
your עירוב, eruv, not for the normal הלכות halachos of carrying, it's
considered like it's all inhabited, it's all filled. In some virtual sense,
it's as if it were רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Now we don't
really mean that, we don't mean that you can carry in the
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or you can carry from the tree to
the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, all of that is still biblically forbidden.
But in terms of conceptually do we say you and your עירוב
eruv are in the same place? So if you're here within the
city, you know, within the environs of the city, then even though
your עירוב eruv is in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and you're
in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. It's all considered to be the
same space. Okay, so this is a big חידוש chiddush *chiddush* that
you don't need, there's this idea of like technically, halachically, you can't
get the עירוב Eiruv *eiruv*, halachically the עירוב Eiruv *eiruv* is in
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid* and you're in a רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim. *reshus harabim*, but somehow if you're in the city,
it's as if you're all together. It's as if the city is
filled, fully inhabited, as if it's like you're all together. Does that
mean even if you couldn't reach the עירוב Eiruv *eiruv*? That's a
good question. That's practically, shouldn't it lead to a גזרה *gezeirah*? Yeah,
it's a strange idea. Where do you get this idea anyway? Why
should we say something like that? I mean we had בי כנישתא
דבי מלווא *bei knishta d'bei malevya* but that was a house surrounded
by walls and that was for a הלכה halakha *halacha* of whether
you needed to do an act of putting it down in the
house. Here we're making it as if virtually as if the רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim. *reshus harabim* becomes a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus
hayachid* which obviously isn't true. So this is a very חידוש chiddush
*chiddush* statement of Rava and it's going to lead us to say
some very weird things about the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. Let's take a
look. Yes. Could it still be considered a כרמלית karmelis *karmelis*? What?
Is the whole
thing...
No, you're in a רשות הרבים Reshus Harabbim. *reshus harabim*, the עירוב
Eiruv *eiruv* is in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshus hayachid*. Oh,
you mean within this concept of it's as if it's all filled.
No, Rashi says as if it's all filled it's like it all
becomes רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. But again we don't really
mean that for carrying purposes, just to conceptualize you and the tree
are in the same space. Okay? So essentially you can reach the
עירוב Eiruv *eiruv* but practically you can't? Exactly,
and that's Michael's question about well if you tell people it's considered
the same space they might come to actually move it and carry
it and so on. Now part of it might be, if it
maybe helps you conceptualize it a little bit more, when I gave
you that example of the whole city is considered to be like
taking up no space, right? So if you could travel into from
city A to city B, then your אלפים אמות amos *alpayim ammos*
it doesn't get deducted based on the space of city B. Everything
of a city doesn't take up any distance. So that could be
the point. If this is within the environs of the city, since
for other ways we consider a city to be one space for
הלכות עירוב hilkhot eruv *hilchos eiruv*, we don't consider it to be,
you know, we consider it to all be like compressed together, so
for the idea of are you in the same space of your
עירוב Eiruv. *eiruv*, we consider it to be that case. Let's see
now what the גמרא Gemara *gemara* does with this. דבכמדי מהי טעמא
*d'b'chemdi mai ta'ama*? אי הכי ei hachi, *ei hachi* says the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* if that's true, חוץ לעיבורה של עיר chutz l'ibura shel
ir, נמי nami, *chutz l'ibburah shel ir nami*, even outside of the
עיבור *ibbur* of the pregnancy of the city, it should be considered
like you're in the same space. Why? כיון דאמר רבא keivan d'amar
Rava, *keivan d'amar Rava*, because Rava says, הנותן עירובו יש לו ד'
אמות amos *hanosen eiruvo yeish lo daled ammos*. Wherever you put your
עירוב Eiruv *eiruv*, you have ד' אמות amos *daled ammos*. הוי ליה
רשות היחיד havei lei reshus hayachid, *havei lei reshus hayachid*, then it
becomes as if it's a private domain, ורשות היחיד עולה עד לרקיע
v'reshus hayachid ola ad l'rakia, *v'reshus hayachid oleh ad l'rakiya* and that
goes up to the heaven. What does that mean? It means, you
put your עירוב Eiruv *eiruv* over here, you put your עירוב Eiruv
*eiruv* at the אלפים *alpayim*, at the אלפים *alpayim* limit, okay? That's
where you put your עירוב Eiruv, *eiruv* right before שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*
began, and then five minutes
before בין השמשות bein hashmashos *bein hashmashos* it happened to roll a
few אמות amos *ammos*, and now it is 2003 אמות amos *ammos*
outside of the city, okay? Now you say, well, it's not in
an accessible place, you can't get to it, right? It's more than
אלפים אמות amot *alpayim ammos* out of the city, it's not within
the אלפים אמות amos, *alpayim ammos*. But Rava says no, no, no.
From wherever you put your עירוב Eiruv *eiruv*, you have ד' אמות
amos, *daled ammos* in each
direction. And therefore
even if it traveled up to ד' אמות amos *daled ammos*, it's
like it hasn't traveled, it's like it's all in the same space.
So the same way we said the city doesn't, you know, take
up any space for הלכות עירוב hilchot eiruv. *hilchos eiruv*, so wherever
you put your עירוב Eiruv? *eiruv* it's like it's in its own
little house and has ד' אמות amos *daled ammos* in every direction
and going in those directions is not like it really traveled, it's
all considered the same essentially the same space. What's the problem? So
it's okay. So that's what Rava says. So now the point is,
ah, so the same way we said that when it's within the
city, since that's all considered one space, it's not a problem of
being in the tree because we have this concept for עירוב Eiruv
*eiruv* purposes it's all considered condensed and one space. So anywhere your
עירוב Eiruv? *eiruv* is, it should not be a problem being in
the tree. Since we say that you have ד' אמות amot *daled
ammos* in every direction and it's all considered like it's all together
and it's all one space and as the גמרא Gemara *gemara* goes
so far to say it's like it's all in a house, it's
all surrounded by walls, then therefore wherever you put your עירוב eruv
*eiruv*, you should always be considered the same space since wherever you
are, you've got like ד' אמות ammot, *daled ammos* in each direction
which is this concept. So again it's an interesting idea that the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* frames it as surrounded by walls, but you don't
really have to and calling it a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus
hayachid*. But conceptually you understand the analogy. The analogy is if for
laws of עירוב eruv *eiruv*, anything in a city is considered to
be all together like just occupying the same space so it doesn't
take up distance, and anywhere an עירוב eruv *eiruv* is, anywhere in
ד' אמות ammot *daled ammos* is not considered to have traveled a
distance, it's all the same space, so even if it's up in
a tree, it should all be considered to be in the same
space and we shouldn't have a
problem of you. No, it's a question on once רבא Rava. says
this idea that it's all the same space, yes, then why does
our משנה Mishnah, have a problem with the עירוב eruv being in
a tree? Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Yeah,
according to רבא. Rava. So it says, אי הכי, I'll read that
again, חוץ לעיבורה של עיר, even if it's not within the environs
of the city, נמי, it should also not be a problem. כיון
דאמר רבא, נותן עירובו יש לו ארבע אמות, noten eiruvo yesh lo
arba amos, wherever you put your עירוב eruv you have ארבע אמות
arba amos in every direction. הוי ליה רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid.
so the whole space around the עירוב eruv is like a private
domain. I would just say it's like it's all one space. ורשות
היחיד עולה עד לרקיע, and who cares if it's in the tree?
So this leads the גמרא Gemara to a
very far-fetched description of the משנה, all because we're trying to defend
רבא. אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב משארשיא, Amar Rav Yitzchak breih d'Rav
Mesharshiya, הכא באילן הנוטה חוץ לארבע אמות עסקינן. hacha b'ilan hanoteh chutz
l'arba amos askinan. Top of ל"ג עמוד ב. lamed gimmel amud beis.
Basically
a branch goes outside of ארבע אמות, arba amos, and you are
trying to be at the base of the tree. I'll just draw
it in a minute. ומאי למעלה ומאי למטה, u'mai l'ma'ala u'mai l'mata,
what does it mean if you put it above ten טפחים tefachim
or below? דהדר זקיף, d'hadar zakif,
that then the branch went up. Basically what we're talking about is
like this. Here you've got your... your עירוב eruv. is up in
the tree there. You've got a branch of the tree... I'll have
to erase my city here. You're erasing your city. Goodbye city. It
doesn't take up any space anyway. Exactly, doesn't take up any space.
You've got a branch of the tree that goes like this, okay?
You've got a branch of the tree. Okay, so what was our
question? Our question is anywhere within ארבע אמות arba amos should all
be considered the same space. Okay, but the problem is you put
your עירוב eruv over here and you wanted to start שבת Shabbos
over here. So it's outside of
ארבע אמות. arba amos. If it were here it wouldn't matter if
it's in a רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid? It's all the same space.
But it's actually over there, and therefore it matters if it's higher
than ten טפחים. tefachim. Actually this would have to be like nine
טפחים tefachim and this here is ten טפחים. tefachim. So if it's
ten טפחים tefachim or higher it's רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid. You can't
get it down to you in a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabbim If
it's lower then it's like a כרמלית karmelis, and it's only a
rabbinic problem and you would be able to get it to you
because again we're not concerned about rabbinic problems. Why is it okay
if it's nine? What? Because then it's in a כרמלית, karmelis, so
it would only be rabbinic to take it from you into the
רשות reshus into where you are and rabbinic issues are not a
problem, right, for בין השמשות bein hashmashos for עירוב. eruv, Now, now
what about the problem that you have to travel more than ארבע
אמות? arba amos? Right, you're not allowed to travel more than ארבע
אמות. arba amos. So תוספות Tosafos says it's not a problem. In
the tree. You only need to travel... if this is like
six אמות ammot this whole branch, you only need to travel two
אמות ammot to get it into the ארבע אמות arba amos zone.
You don't have to travel four. רש"י Rashi says you can take
multiple little steps and each time go less than ארבע אמות. arba
amos. But the point is rabbinically you'd be able... if it were
less than ten טפחים, tefachim, you'd be able rabbinically to get it
to you. I mean only with rabbinic violation you'd be able to
get it with you. When it's higher, then again we have the
רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid, רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim It's exactly what we
said before, except to get out of the challenge that if it's
within ארבע אמות arba amos it shouldn't matter, we say okay, it's
a special case and it's not within ארבע אמות. arba amos. What
do you need the tree for? What? I could... I could put
my עירוב eruv. a mile away on the end. Right, and do
tiny little steps up. So that is an excellent question which the
גמרא Gemara does not directly address because until now we've been saying
that you and the עירוב eruv? are in the same space, except
it's maybe too high and it's a רשות היחיד. Reshus Hayachid, But
if we're saying that it could be distance, right, so then Dov
asks an excellent question. So then I don't get it. Why don't
I put my עירוב eruv. here and say I'm planning to start
שבת Shabbos over there? Right? You're not physically here. You're saying I'm
conceptually saying I'm starting שבת Shabbos at the base of the tree.
But don't you have to start שבת Shabbos. not only where you
can access your עירוב, eruv. but where your עירוב eruv actually is?
How can it be six אמות ammot, outside of where you are?
So that is an excellent question. We're going to see some of
that either at the end of the day or beginning of tomorrow,
but I would say at least here it's better because it's all
connected to the same tree, and that might make it better. But
Dov is absolutely correct that a key question to ask is what?
You don't have to be in the same space as your עירוב?
eruv. It can be six אמות amos away from you? So that
is a truly a problem which the גמרא Gemara is not addressing.
Right now it's just focusing on the fact that you can get
it to you without
violating a biblical problem. But if it's within ארבע אמות, arba amos,
then we have this idea that it's all considered together. Wait, let's
have some more questions. Actually, at בין השמשות bein hashmashos. you should
be able to walk a lot further than ארבע אמות. arba amos.
Walk you can, but how can you carry the עירוב eruv to
you? That's the question. Can you access the עירוב? eruv As soon
as you get it out of the tree, you're taking it from
רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid and now would
you... you'd be bringing it to... that's why if
it's in a כרמלית, karmelis, it's okay. But the problem is not
the distance, the problem is the carrying. The way I'm understanding is
like, you know, isn't like the whole under the... The tree, the
tree and whatever is under it, should all be considered one space.
So forget the, I don't understand why you need a four אמות
problem. It's like saying it's in my house. It's not like I
say oh to the edge of the wall's more than four אמות
I can't do anything. Well that's, well okay, the גמרא'ס Gemara's trying
to split the difference. To say within a four אמות, that's so
much one space that even if it's up in a tree, we
would say it's okay, even if it's in a רשות היחיד. Reshus
Hayachid. More than that is I think Dov's question about how can
you not be where your עירוב eruv. is? But that's what I'm
saying, I think it is where your עירוב eruv. is. The whole
thing is where your עירוב eiruv is, it's one space! I understand.
So okay, so that's how you think about like, I understand that
98% of the tree is 0.2% of the tree. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara is looking at it that way. But I understand why!
Well because it doesn't agree with your assumption that everything in the
tree is one space. Why not? Because it's not. Why is it
if it's a branch above ten טפחים, tefachim, why is that רשות
היחיד? Reshus Hayachid. Ah so because if it's ten טפחים tefachim and
assuming the branch is four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים. tefachim. Now
here's the other thing though. תוספות Tosfos says I don't get it,
even if it's in this type of a branch, right, תוספות Tosfos
says we're going to see this in a minute. If you have
something that's suspended and this is ten טפחים tefachim off the ground
and it's four טפחים tefachim by a platform, four טפחים tefachim by
four טפחים, tefachim, right, we normally say that's not a רשות היחיד.
Reshus Hayachid, We'll see that, but because you know it's the problem
that if you can have like a goats go under it, right,
you know it's if it's if it's you know you can't have
a suspended מחיצה, mechitza, right, because nothing is preventing travel underneath. So
תוספות Tosfos says I don't get why that works. Normally if it's
higher than three טפחים tefachim off the ground it shouldn't matter. So
תוספות Tosfos says well what we would be talking about would be
that it's not just ten טפחים tefachim off the ground, but the
branch itself is ten טפחים tefachim high. The branch itself is ten
טפחים. tefachim. So this really is like a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid
right, because you know just in itself. Not because it creates down
to the ground a רשות היחיד, Reshus Hayachid it in itself is
a רשות היחיד Reshus Hayachid and therefore wherever you put it you'll
be putting it like in the zone of a רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid Anyway תוספות Tosfos does ask that question about why does it
work if it's suspended in mid-air. But the basic point
is that yes the branch is ten טפחים tefachim off the ground,
right, it's ten טפחים tefachim off the ground the branch and therefore
if it's four by four טפחים tefachim wide and therefore the branch
is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid Okay and that's the problem but
we have oh we have the branch, excuse me, going like this
because
so then it says here's the case. If you put it at
the ten טפחים tefachim space you put it in a רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid you put it lower you put it in a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim Okay so now or in a כרמלית, karmelis. if
you put it lower it's not a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, and
then you're able to carry it to you. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara now says, okay.
It says like
this.
It says like this. Now דהא אי בעי מייתי ליה דרך
עליו, deha i ba'ei meisi lei derech alav, גמרא Gemara says I
don't get it even if it's higher than ten טפחים tefachim and
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid you can get it to you. How
can you get it to you? So basically what תוספות Tosfos said
I'll give you תוספות'ס Tosfos's version which is easier than רש"י. Rashi.
Here it is, it's ten טפחים tefachim off the ground, this is
nine טפחים tefachim where before it starts bending up, okay. Now if
you took it from here to here you'd be taking it from
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, to a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and that's
a problem. But why not, this is the way תוספות Tosfos sees
it, you take it from here and put it down on the
branch. The branch lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, nine טפחים tefachim or
eight טפחים tefachim is a כרמלית. karmelis, That's okay, that's only rabbinic,
right? And once it's on the branch then you can take it
down to you. Right, so you can get it to you. You
don't have anything going directly this way, there's a way to get
it to you only doing a rabbinic problem by bringing it to
stop at the branch and then taking it from the branch to
you. That's how the גמרא'ס Gemara's question, I don't get it says
the גמרא Gemara you can still get it to you. One minute.
So the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is כשדרבים מכתפין עליו. kesherabbim mekatfin alav.
No, because the branch is something that people lay their packages on.
The branch even nine טפחים tefachim people use. וכידאולא uche'd'Ulla like עולא
Ulla says, דאמר עולא de'amar Ulla עמוד תשעה ברשות הרבים amud tisha
bi'reshus harabbim רבים מכתפין עליו, rabbim mekatfin alav,
if you have a platform in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim that's nine
טפחים tefachim high and people use it as a platform to like
put down their packages so it's regularly used by the רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim. people, וזרק ונח על גביו vezorak venach al gabei and
you throw something from רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, and it lands on
that platform, חייב. chayav. You're חייב. chayav. So even though normally higher
than three טפחים tefachim in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. airspace is a
כרמלית, karmelit. it's not part of the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. if
it's off of three טפחים, tefachim, okay but if it's like meaning
if it's its own מקום makom like you have I don't know
a mailbox, you have something that's its own type of a space
that's higher than three טפחים tefachim off, but if it's nine טפחים
tefachim and it's exactly in this usable position then it becomes considered
part of רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's question is
why not you can still do it in two stages and the
answer is since people use this branch and it's in a perfect
location to be used, the branch itself is רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
So there is no way to get it from this רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid. position to you. Because everywhere around you is a רשות
הרבים. reshut harabim, And therefore, if it's ten טפחים tefachim it's no
good, lower than ten טפחים tefachim you are okay. So again, this
is the גמרא'ס Gemara's basic point: you have to be able to
access your עירוב eiruv because of this idea that within four אמות,
it should all be considered to be all together, we had to
have a special case that it was more than four אמות away
from you. There's no way to get it without violating שבת. Shabbos?
And the only question that I think that we're really left with
is those questions, which is: since when can your עירוב eiruv start
six אמות away from where you're planning on starting שבת? Shabbos Yes,
I'm gonna ask the question, you're gonna say I'm gonna ask it
anyway. איכפל תנא לאשמועינן כל האי? Ichpal tana lashmi’inan kol hai? Yeah,
whatever. So it's all just a דחק dachak explanation in order to
defend רב'ס Rav's position. So if you ask me is רב Rav
פשט, peshat, the answer is absolutely not. It's only a problem according
to רב Rav that the משנה'ס Mishna's talking about a very weird
branch that's swinging upward and it's a branch that everyone uses and
you're coming למטה lemata and it's למעלה. lemala. Yes. Okay, so now
moving on. מאי רבי ומאי רבנן? Mai Rabbi umai Rabbanan? Now we
get to okay, now that we've resolved that, what's the debate of
רבי Rabbi and the רבנן? Rabbanan? Because we said all of this
only works with רבי'ס Rabbi's position that you can do דרבננס de-rabbanans
during בין השמשות. bein hashmashos? So as long as you can get
to the עירוב eiruv with only violating a דרבנן, de-rabbanan, you're safe.
So where is this position of רבי Rabbi and the רבנן Rabbanan
who argue on him whether דרבננס de-rabbanans are allowed בין השמשות? bein
hashmashot. דתניא, De-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Baraita: נתנו באילן למעלה
מעשרה טפחים אין עירובו עירוב. Nasno be-ilan lemala me-asara tefachim ein eruvo
eruv. Higher than ten טפחים tefachim no good because again it's רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid, you're רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
למטה מעשרה טפחים עירובו עירוב. Lemata me-asara tefachim eruvo eruv. Lower than
ten טפחים tefachim it's good, you're in the same zone as your
עירוב. eiruv But ואסור ליטלו. ve-asur litlo. You can't take it off
of the tree because taking it off the tree is on שבת
Shabbat itself is using מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, using something attached to
the ground. So yes you're in the same zone, but you can't
take it off the tree because then you're using the tree.
בתוך שלשה, Betoch shelosha, if it's within three of the ground, it's
on the tree but within three
טפחים, tefachim, מותר ליטלו, muttar litlo, you can even take it because
it's not considered the tree. Within three of the ground, even though
it's on the tree, it's considered part of the ground. So if
it's like on a you know it's on a it's on a
stump or it's on a root that's raised off the ground, anything
within three is considered on the ground, not on the tree. All
right, so the basic חידוש chiddush. of all of this being that
if it's in between three and ten טפחים, tefachim, it works even
though you're not allowed to take it off the tree.
נתנו בכלכלה, Nasno be-kalkala, now if you put it in a
basket and you suspended the basket from the tree, אפילו למעלה מעשרה
טפחים עירובו עירוב. afilu lemala me-asara tefachim eruvo eruv. It works even
higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. So that's unclear why, shouldn't that be
a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. don't we be back to the same
problem? We'll see about that in a minute. דברי רבי, Divrei Rabbi,
that's what רבי Rabbi says. וחכמים אומרים, Ve-Chachamim omrim, but the חכמים
Chachamim say, כל מקום שאסור ליטלו אין עירובו עירוב. kol makom she-asur
litlo ein eruvo eruv. I'm sorry, if you can't get your עירוב
eiruv off of the tree, then it doesn't count. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says וחכמים אומרים אהיי, ve-Chachamim omrim aha'i, which case are
the חכמים Chachamim arguing on? אילימא אסיפא, Ileima a-seifa,
if they're arguing on the last case, the basket. Maybe they're saying
the basket is in, you're not allowed to take it from the
basket, that's אסור asur to take. So if that's true, the גמרא
Gemara says that's not so clear they would argue on that. לימא
קסבר רבנן צדדין אסורין? Leima kasavar Rabbanan tzedadin asurin? Would that imply
that the רבנן Rabbanan say that you can't even use the side
of a מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, meaning if you remember we basically
פסקן pasken from an earlier גמרא Gemara that
there's your again your tree, okay, there's your tree, okay. Now if
you've got, here's a branch. If you've got a basket hanging from,
that's an awful basket, anyway, if you've got a basket hanging from
the branch, so you're not directly using the tree but you're using
something that is connected to the tree, that's called צדדין. tzedadin. And
there's a question, are you allowed to do that? A similar more
common example would be can you sleep in a hammock here, okay,
because the hammock is directly attached to the tree. Okay, that's צדדין.
tzedadin. If however the hammock is attached to a nail, you know,
or there's a you know or the basket is attached to a
nail, then that's okay because that's צידי צדדין. tzidei tzedadin. It's it's
two degrees removed from the tree. Okay, so that was debated. So
the גמרא Gemara says if when the חכמים Chachamim are saying, "Hey,
you can't access your עירוב," eiruv if they're talking about the basket
case, that that sort of you know locks them into a particular
position that צדדין אסורין. tzedadin asurin. And we don't want to be
locked into a position even though that's how we פסקן, pasken, we
don't want them locked into that position. אלא, Ella, rather, anyway, this
makes more sense. ארישא. A-reisha. They're going on the first case. So
what it says is base, I mean where basically רבי Rabbi says
if it's between three and ten טפחים, tefachim, it's okay even though
you can't take, even though you can't take it off the tree.
Okay, and the חכמים Chachamim say, "I'm sorry, if you can't take
it off the tree, then it can't count as an עירוב." eiruv
So this is the debate between the חכמים Chachamim and רבי, Rabbi,
which is if something is rabbinically forbidden to access, can it count
as an עירוב? eiruv. Now I do want to tell you that
the גמרא Gemara, is quite amazing how it how it abstracted
רבי'ס Rabbi's position. Because based on this ברייתא... Baraita... All רבי Rebbe
says is even though there's a rabbinic problem, it still counts as
an עירוב. eiruv So his הלכה halakha might just completely have been
in הלכות עירובין, hilkhot eruvin, right? Like within הלכות עירובין hilkhot eruvin
like before we said, it's all in one city, it's like it's
all in one space. So there could have been, as long as
you can get it and it's only a rabbinic obstacle, it's considered
to be accessible. Fine, that's a הלכה halakha that counts as an
עירוב. eruv The גמרא Gemara abstracted it to say that according to
רבי, Rebbe, you can do דרבננס d'rabanans בין השמשות. bein hashmashot.
It's not just a דין din in הלכות hilchot עירוב eruv, that
it's not considered an obstacle. It's a general הלכה you can do
דרבננס d'rabanans בין השמשות. bein hashmashot Now I should say as I
told you before, we by the way, we פסקן pasken רבי, Rebbe,
but with two caveats. Caveat number one is, is that remember we
had the idea that you can only make an עירוב eruv. לצורך
מצוה. l'tzorech mitzvah. So a lot of פוסקים poskim say, oh, you
can only do דרבננס d'rabanans בין השמשות bein hashmashot. לצורך מצוה, l'tzorech
mitzvah, like in the context of the עירוב. eruv. The other caveat
is, is that if you've already done קבלת שבת, Kabbalat Shabbat, or
on the out- or going out if you haven't done הבדלה, Havdalah,
you know, you can do הבדלה Havdalah not by a fire, but
you can make הבדלה Havdalah before שבת Shabbat. is out. Anyway, so
then it doesn't apply because then you subjectively have still declared that
time to already be שבת. Shabbat But anyway, it's quite fascinating that
the גמרא Gemara takes a debate between רבי Rebbe and the חכמים
hachamim of if an עירוב eruv. is on a tree and you
rabbinically you can't get to it, רבי Rebbe says biblically you can,
not rabbinically because you can't use a tree, רבי Rebbe says it
counts as an עירוב eruv and the חכמים hachamim say no, and
that becomes the idea that according to רבי Rebbe you can do
דרבננס d'rabanans בין השמשות. bein hashmashot Okay? So why do you have
between the three and ten problem according to רבי? Rebbe? It's not
a problem, it works according to רבי. Rebbe. רבי Rebbe says אסור
ליטלו, assur litlo, on שבת Shabbat. itself you can't take it, but
it's only a rabbinic issue and therefore it counts as an עירוב.
eruv The חכמים hachamim say I'm sorry, if you can't take it
then it doesn't count as an עירוב. eruv What was that הבדלה
Havdalah you said? I understand the קידוש Kiddush part. You said about...
what was your... if you make הבדלה Havdalah without lighting a candle
obviously, you can make הבדלה Havdalah already as early as פלג המנחה.
plag hamincha. Okay, again לצורך מצוה l'tzorech mitzvah and you're not going
to have time מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbat or whatever. So that's according
to a lot of פוסקים poskim is necessary if you want to
use רבי's Rebbe position of דרבננס d'rabanans בין השמשות bein hashmashot. by
מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbat, because else you still have your own subjective
definition of it being שבת. Shabbat All right, anyway so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, האי אילן היכי דמי? Hai ilan heichi dami?
Now this tree, what's the case? אי די לית ביה ארבעה, I
dei leit be arba, so this is basically also clarifying what we
spoke about before. Why is this tree a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
when it's ten טפחים t'fachim off the ground? If the you sort
of, you know, the branch or whatever it is is not four
by four טפחים, t'fachim, you know, in terms of width and depth,
מקום פטור הוא. mekom p'tur hu. So it's not considered a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid, it's a מקום פטור, mekom p'tur, it's a no-man's
land. You're allowed to carry from that to רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
אי די אית ביה ארבעה, I dei it be arba, now if
you actually have four by four טפחים t'fachim and that's why it's
a problem when it's higher than ten, it's a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid. which is what we've been assuming. So כי נתנו בכלכלה, ki
natno bekalkala, so let's go to the end case that רבי Rebbe
said if you put it in a basket it's okay, so מאי
הוה? mai hava? So why all of a sudden did רבי Rebbe
agree it's okay if you put it in a basket, right? So
here you've got your case about your
I don't know for רש"י, Rashi, where he says we're still assuming
it's weird thin branch, but it doesn't matter, okay? So here, if
you put it at ten טפחים t'fachim limit it's no good cause
that's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, Okay, and we have to assume
that it's four by four טפחים. t'fachim. Okay, and therefore it's no
good if you put it there. So says the גמרא, Gemara why
does רבי Rebbe all of a sudden say that if you've got
a basket hanging and you put it in the basket, why all
of a sudden is it now okay? It's ten טפחים t'fachim off
the ground, it's presumably connected to this branch, which is a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid. so it's part of a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid
Why all of a sudden according to רבי Rebbe when you put
it in a basket that's higher than ten טפחים t'fachim does it
become good? Okay so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. כי נתנו בכלכלה
מאי הוה? Ki natno bekalkala mai hava? Who cares that you put
it in a basket? So אמר רבינא Amar Ravina says רבינא, Ravina,
רישא דאית ביה ארבעה, reisha dei it be arba, the first case
where on the branch it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid is yeah
the branch is four by four. סיפא, Seifa, the second case, the
end case of the basket where it's okay is a- it's four
by four but only with the basket. דלית ביה ארבעה, De leit
be arba, the branch itself is not four by
four, וכלכלה משלמתה לארבעה vekalkala mashlimta l'arba and only with the basket
does it become four by four. So basically the way it looks
is like, you know, here's your branch, this is four טפחים, t'fachim,
this is two טפחים, t'fachim, here's your branch, okay, very rectangular branch.
And here's a basket that you are suspending from the branch, okay,
you're suspending. Here we'll make the branch circular so it looks more
like a tree anyway, and here's your basket. So this is two-
this is two טפחים, t'fachim, this is two טפחים, t'fachim, so therefore
together with the basket you have a space of four by four
טפחים. t'fachim. You got the scenario? Okay. And now we're going to
say why all of a sudden- but so what? It's four by
four טפחים t'fachim why still it should be a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid why is that מותר? muttar? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
ורבי סבר לה כרבי מאיר Ve-Rebbe savar lah ke-Rabbi Meir the top
of ל"ג ע"ב, lamed gimmel amud bet, רבי Rebbe holds like רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, וסבר לה כרבי יהודה ve-savar lah ke-Rabbi Yehuda and
holds like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. סבר לה כרבי מאיר דאמר חוקקין
להשלים. savar lah k'Rebbi Meir de-amar chokekin lehashlim. He holds like רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir that says we envision something as if it's carved
out in order to see it as if it has the whole
שיעור. shiur. Okay, so the example of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was,
right we had this at the beginning, you basically have an archway,
okay, but it is not, in order for it to be a
מזוזה, mezuzah, it had to be four by four, right here it's
four, but for, you know, here it's four אמות but not at
the top. So you envision as if this is cut out, so
it's considered to be the archway is the right parameters for a
מזוזה. mezuzah. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says sometimes you envision that
in theory you could create the necessary space and that works. Okay,
that's point number
one. וסבר לה כרבי יהודה דאמר בעינן עירוב על גבי מקום ארבעה
דליכא v'savar lah k'Rebbi Yehuda d'amar ba'inan eiruv al gabei makom arba'ah
d'leika that you need an עירוב eruv on a place that's four
by four טפחים. tefachim. If you put your עירוב eruv on a
smaller space, it doesn't count, and you would not have that here
unless you actually carved it out. So what does that mean? It
means, because the גמרא's Gemara basically saying, what's the חידוש chiddush? of
the basket case? So it says, here's the חידוש. chiddush If it
were just, if you just viewed your עירוב eruv. in the basket,
so it's in a space
of two טפחים, tefachim, and we're going to say that for an
עירוב eruv to count, it has to be in a, what's called
a significant space. Normally halachically, if it's less than four by four
טפחים, tefachim, the reason that's a מקום פטור makom patur is it's
not a real space. So for an עירוב eruv to count, it
has to be in a space of four טפחים. tefachim. How do
you get in a space of four טפחים tefachim if it's in
this basket? You look at it as if you carved out the
space in the branch that it's connected to, so as if it
has the whole space of four טפחים. tefachim. That's the חוקקין להשלים.
chokekin lehashlim. Now all of that is quite lovely and fascinating, but
the question is, great! But now you're back to the problem that
it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay, so if you're back to
the problem that it's a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. right, why, back
to the question of why is this not an issue? So רש"י,
Rashi, let me just check רש"י Rashi before I give the answer,
just double check.
Right.
So רש"י Rashi says, of course the problem is that then why
wasn't this the case in the middle? רש"י Rashi says that it's
similar to the issues that תוספות Tosafot sort of raised before. Yes,
you have four טפחים tefachim up here, but if you think about
it, right, let's not say the case of the extended branch, let's
look at just like a straight trunk. If you think about it,
you've got four טפחים tefachim up there, but how much do you
have at the base? Right, what did I say that this was?
It was two by four but you had the basket up here.
So at the base, right, of this thing, it's not four by
four, it's four by two. Right, only up here do you have
it four by four. So רש"י Rashi says that's not a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid, It's not a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. because רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid it has to be four by four even at
the base. Okay? So this is a case where it works as
an עירוב eruv because it's virtually four by four, you view it
as if it's carved out, but it does not, it's not a
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, problem because it's only four by four at
the top and not four by four at the base. והא פשוטו
דאוירא ושדי. v'ha pishuto d'avira v'shadi. Yeah, so that's the problem. Here
we said when the branch extended out, even it was four by
four at the top, it's like it goes all the way down.
How come here we're all of a sudden switching gears? Yeah, so
it's a problem. I mean תוספות Tosafot makes this into a, this
one into a special case, but anyway, it's very complicated. But the
upshot is, why does the basket work according to רבי? Rebbi? So
the easy answer is it works because it's not a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. It's a case where
that the base of it is not four by four, it's not
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, So then what's the חידוש? So the
חידוש is not only is it not a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid
but it counts for being a place of four by four because
of this idea of חוקקין להשלים. chokekin lehashlim. Again, very sort of
complicated explanation and you really wonder if like is that really פשט,
pshat, but that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so מאי רבי
יהודה? mai Rebbi Yehuda? Now where is this position of רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda that we've now introduced, that you need an עירוב eruv
to be on a space of four by four? דתניא, D'tanya, we
learned a ברייתא. baraita. רבי יהודה אומר נעץ קורה ברשות הרבים והניחו
עירוב עליה, Rebbi Yehuda omer na'atz koreh b'reshut harabim v'hinnicho eiruv aleha,
you put a pole in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim a simple like
you know flagpole, and you put your עירוב eruv on
it. גבוה י' ורחבו ד' עירובו עירוב, gavo'ah yud v'rochavo arba'ah eiruvo
eiruv, it counts. This is a little funny, right, because that would
seem to be ten high four by four is a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. But he says it counts. ואם לאו אין עירובו עירוב.
v'im lav ein eiruvo eiruv. It doesn't count. This is the exact
opposite of what you would expected. Ten by fours is usually a
problem. So now let's see how the גמרא Gemara analyzes it. So
the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה adiraba the opposite. הוא ועירוב במקום אחד,
hu v'eiruv b'makom echad, if it's lower than ten, it should be
better, you're in the same space as your עירוב. eruv אלא הכי
קאמר, ella hachi ka'amar, here's how to read
it. גבוה עשרה צריך שיהא בראשו ארבעה. gavo'ah asarah tzarich she-ye-hei b'rosho
arba'ah. needs to be four by four at the top. אין גבוה
עשרה, Ein gavoah asarah, אין צריך שיהיה בראשו ארבעה. ein tzarich sheyehe
berosho arba'ah. And if it's not ten, it does not have to
be four by four. What does this mean? It means again you've
got your post here, which
is whatever, you've got your, which is ten טפחים tefachim high. And
you're here. Now the first question is, so he says, it needs
to be four by four over here. Now the first question is,
but then it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and you're in a
רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim, Why does it work? So רש"י Rashi again
introduces this idea that anything within four אמות, right, is considered to
be in the same space, like we said before, the four אמות
rule. So don't worry about the fact that it's a רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid? you're in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim It's all the
special case we said before, within four אמות you're safe. Fine. So
we're not going to worry it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So
if it's higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, it has to be four
by four. If it's lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, then even if
this is like three by three, it's okay. Why? So conceptually here's
the point. Lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, it's considered to some degree,
we're doing a lot of virtual things,
anything within four אמות is the same place, etc. So less than
ten טפחים tefachim is like it's on the ground. Not again for
הלכות hilchot carrying. I know. Not הלכות carrying, but for הלכות עירוב.
eruv, It's like it's right with you. So then it doesn't need
to have its own space four by
four because the air space of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim, goes into
ten—up to ten טפחים. tefachim. It's within the רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim?
it doesn't need to have its own space of four by four.
So less than ten טפחים, tefachim, it counts whatever, however thick the
pole is. Higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, if it's in its own
space, right? The air space of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim doesn't go
higher than ten טפחים. tefachim. Ah, it's its own space. It doesn't
count as being somewhere unless the space is four by four טפחים.
tefachim. Okay, but again, what's very bizarre is we've normally always assumed
that that's bad. So again, because you're within four אמות, it's all
the same, etc. But now we have a case where again we're
sort of labeling it as a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. creating that
scenario actually works rather than doesn't work. And this is how we
see that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is of the position since he
emphasized four by four טפחים tefachim as a requirement rather than as
a problem, that when something is out of the air space of
רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, it only counts as an עירוב eruv if
it's on a space of four by four טפחים tefachim because that's
like it's in a real location. Okay. Who gave you rights to
be putting these עירובים eiruvin in רשות הרבים? reshut harabim, Yeah, okay,
that's a question. What could I tell? That's not what's bothering the
גמרא Gemara now. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says, כמאן? Keman? Now
this idea that we have said that if you suspend something, the
way רש"י Rashi reads this is we're going back to our basket
case. So our basket case was, it was four by two, and
then you suspended the basket and the basket made it four by
four. And according to רש"י, Rashi, the reason it's not a רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid, is because at the base it's only like four
by two, and therefore it's not a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. That's
what רש"י Rashi says. So where do we get this idea that
even though it's four by four up here at ten, it's not
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, because of the bottom? That's what רש"י's
Rashi going to understand the גמרא Gemara is now
asking. כמאן? Keman? Who is this going like? That if at the
base it's not four by four, it's not a רשות היחיד? reshut
hayachid דלא כרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Dela keRabbi Yosi beRabbi Yehuda. Not
like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yosi beRabbi Yehuda. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yosi
beRabbi Yehuda omer, נעץ קנה ברשות הרבים והניח בראשו טרסקל. na'atz kaneh
birshut harabbim vehiniach berosho terraskal.
You put a pole in רשות הרבים reshut harabim, and you put
a basket on the top. וזרק ונח לגביו חייב. Vezarak venach legabav
chayav. And you threw and it landed on it, it's חייב. chayav.
So that's a very simple case. Here's your pole. Here's your basket.
Okay, the basket is four by four. It's higher than ten טפחים
tefachim off the ground, and you threw something into it from a
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. you're חייב. chayav. That's a רשות היחיד. reshut
hayachid So basically, what is he saying is, as long as you
have a platform four by four higher than ten טפחים, tefachim, it's
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, So if that's true, why isn't this
case a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid which is what you guys asked
before, and I said because of the base. Well, there's no base
here, it's a pole. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ah, you
see that it contradicts. So the גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה. Afilu teima Rabbi Yosi beRabbi Yehuda. No, it can
even work according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yosi beRabbi Yehuda.
התם הדרא מחיצתא. Hatam hadra mechitzta. There the מחיצתא mechitzta go around
it. הכא לא הדרא מחיצתא. Hacha lo hadra mechitzta. Here they do
not go around it, which means what? In this case of the
basket, you envision it like the walls of the basket descend and
create a space at the bottom that's four by two surrounded by
walls. Okay, here you really only
have you don't have like a space up here that's surrounded by
a four by four thing, you have a two by four thing
here and a two by four thing here. So somehow, again, I
don't really get why this is so substantively different, but somehow you
can't just descend this and create this space because again also part
of this is the actual beam. So you won't really have an
open space surrounded by four by four at the bottom. bottom the
same way you will in גוד אחית, gud achit, it's a little
bit different. What?
Yeah, right. Anyway, all of this is, right, remember just yesterday we
were talking about חזקה שליח עושה שליחותו. hazakah shaliach oseh shelichuto. How
radically different these דפים dafim are. Okay, so but anyway, that's the
basic point that whatever you say about the case of the basket
on the pole, this case is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid So
let's just review what we have said basically. You and the עירוב
eruv have to be in the same space, according means you have
to be able to access it הלכתית. halachically. According to רבי, Rebbi,
even if it only requires a rabbinic violation, I'm sorry, if it
only requires a rabbinic violation, it's still considered accessible הלכתית, halachically, which
the גמרא Gemara, abstracts to mean that that you can do rabbinic
prohibitions during בין השמשות. bein hashmashos
And but if it's in a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid you're in
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. no good. However, there's this other idea the
גמרא Gemara says that anywhere within ארבע אמות arba amot where you
begin, it's like it's all the same space. And therefore it would
be good to create these very special scenarios that are not a
branch outside of ארבע אמות. arba amot. The obvious thing that we
have seen is this idea that an עירוב, if it's out higher
than the airspace of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. has to be on
a place ארבע על ארבע arba al arba to be considered in
a place. And the most recent thing the גמרא's Gemara discussing is
this case of the basket and the tree and whatnot, which is
if it's
ten high and ארבע על ארבע arba al arba at the top,
but not at the bottom, is that considered a רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid or not? Okay, let's now see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
Okay, רבי ירמיה אמר. Rebbi Yirmiyah amar. Now רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmiyah
goes back to the whole basket case. Why the basket, why is
it okay? So we gave this whole scenario about it not being
in a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, and חוקקין להשלים. chokekin lehashlim. He
says no, no, no. Here's why the basket is okay. שאני כלכלה,
shani kalkalah, the basket is different, הואיל ויכול להטותה ולהביאה לתוך עשרה,
ho'il veyachol lehatotah ulehavi'ah letoch asarah,
because you can tip the basket over. You've got it in this
basket connected to the tree. It's now in a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid, right? You're here at the bottom in a רשות הרבים. reshut
harabim. But what you can do is you can tip the basket,
okay, and the food can sort of slide down to you and
therefore
you can actually get to it. Now the question is what do
you mean? If it slides down to you and you get to
it, you're taking it from a רשות היחיד into a רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. Okay, but no, first because if you tip the basket
down, it goes lower than ten טפחים tefachim and now the food
slides into it, the food is lower than ten טפחים, tefachim, it's
in like nine טפחים, tefachim, it's in a כרמלית. karmelit So basically
if all you have is the tree and you, if all you
have is the tree and you, then all you have is a
רשות היחיד and a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, Now I don't know
why he can't say you can't take it off the tree and
put it in a different place on the tree, but in the
process you'll be taking it, you're holding it and you're in a
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, Okay, so you'll be actually taking it from
the רשות היחיד into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim But because it's
in a basket, you can tilt it and without ever taking it
to you in the רשות הרבים, you brought it into a כרמלית
and then it's a special case, the גמרא, Gemara your basket you
know, right, it's tiltable. But that's a much easier explanation for רבי.
Rebbi. Forget all this חוקקין להשלים, chokekin lehashlim, it's רשות היחיד on
the top, not on the bottom. None of that. If it's in
the tree and it's רשות היחיד, it's a problem because then
you would have to violate שבת Shabbat to get to it. If
it's in a basket, by tipping the basket, you can do it
in two stages and it's considered accessible. Assuming the basket is going
down. Yeah,
exactly. You did it really high. Exactly. Okay. What? Oh, it's better
than taking it, you know, and doing it manually rather than tilting
it. Because that's what I'm saying, if you do it manually and
you're standing in a רשות הרבים, as soon as you take something
out of רשות היחיד, it's defined by your feet. Oh, if you
could actually move it on the tree without actually but that would
also be like a very special scenario, right? If it's on a
branch of a tree to move it to a lower branch you'd
have to take it off and then you'd have to take it
into רשות הרבים exactly at ten טפחים tefachim and you tilt the
basket. Well, doesn't matter if it's exactly ten טפחים, tefachim, it matters
if it ends up lower than ten טפחים. tefachim. Yeah, something like
that. I mean, you got to be very careful. I know. Anyway,
I got to tell you though it's a much simpler explanation than
the first one. Okay, יתיב רב פפא, yativ Rav Pappa, let's read
a little bit more. יתיב רב פפא וקאמר להאי שמעתא. yativ Rav
Pappa veka'amar lehai shema'ata. רב פפא Rav Pappa was sitting and telling
over this whole discussion. איתיביה
רב שבא לרב פפא, eitiveh Rav Shava leRav Pappa, so רב שבא
Rav Shava asked רב פפא, Rav Pappa, כיצד הוא עושה? keitzad hu
oseh? So here we have a general principle of making an עירוב.
And this is the case about שבת Shabbat. and יום טוב, Yom
Tov, but it's really quoted, רש"י Rashi says it's just to discuss
the general reality of making an עירוב. So what do you do?
You need to make an עירוב. Now here the case is that
it's יום טוב Yom Tov leading into שבת. Shabbat. And you want
this to be a good עירוב for יום טוב Yom Tov and
for שבת. Shabbat. But you're concerned that if you leave the עירוב
out there for two days or whatever, it's going to get eaten.
So you want to protect your עירוב so you can use it
tomorrow. Right, today is Thursday late afternoon. You want it to work
for Friday יום טוב Yom Tov and for שבת. shabbos, You need
it to be there late Friday afternoon. So what do you do?
כיצד הוא עושה? keitzad hu oseh? What do you do? מוליכו בראשון,
molicho barishon, bring it out to the place you need it on
the first day, meaning
on
ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, on Thursday. Carry. So בנטלו, benotlo,
then you pick it up, ובא לו u'va lo and bring it
home. בשני bashani and then the next day, Friday late afternoon, which
is יום טוב, yom tov, you can still carry. מחשיך עליו, machshich
alav, you bring it to the space, ואוכלו v'ochlo and then if
you don't want it to go to waste, you can't carry it
anymore, now it's שבת, shabbos. so you eat it. ובא לו u'va
lo and you come home. Okay, so that's just a describing a
scenario of making an עירוב in a case of יום טוב yom
tov and שבת. shabbos By the way, רש"י Rashi says why if
you're actually going there and you're waiting till it gets dark, you
don't need the food? If you're actually in the place where you
want to start שבת shabbos when it gets dark, the whole idea
of the עירוב is a substitute for your presence. So רש"י Rashi
says this is a case where you're not bringing it, you're asking
your friend, וחזקה שליח עושה
שליחותו. v'chazaka shliach oseh shlichuso. So I'm asking Michael to bring it
there, so his presence doesn't count for my presence. He actually have
to put the food down. Okay, but that's a scenario of making
an עירוב. So what does that have to do with the basket?
So let's take a look. And this sort of also gets to
Dov's question about on the tree outside of שש אמות. shesh amos.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמאי? amai? According to רש"י,
Rashi, this is a mind-boggling question. It's basically the question is: forget
שבת shabbos. and יום טוב. yom tov. Why do you ever have
to bring your עירוב to the place you want it? נימא כיון
דאי בעי ליה מצי מטי ליה naima keivan d'ee bei lei matzi
mati lei since in theory you could bring it to you by
making like a lot of little trips less than ארבע אמות arba
amos מצי מטי ליה matzi mati lei אף על גב דלא מטי
ליה. af al gav d'lo mati lei. So it's as if you
could bring it even though you didn't bring it. So כמאן דמטי
ליה דמי, k'man d'mati lei dami, it's like you brought it. Meaning
the גמרא Gemara is finally getting fed up, is a way of
reading it. It's like: oh, in theory you could tip the basket
and bring it this way, and if it's on the branch six
אמות out, I could maybe put it on the branch and then
from the branch to the this and in theory I could da-da-da-da-da.
Okay even though right now it's not directly accessible. So the גמרא
Gemara says: so even if it's very distant, who ever have to
put an עירוב anywhere? In theory your עירוב could be in your
front yard and oh, because בין השמשות bein hashmashos I could have
made a lot of little trips and gotten it to where I
needed it to get it to. Or not even. So why do
you ever need to put your עירוב anywhere? So let's see what
that's the way רש"י Rashi understands the question. So let's see what
the גמרא's answer is going to be. A mind-boggling answer, we'll worry
about that tomorrow, just read the answer for now. So אמר רבי
זירא גזירה משום יום טוב שחל להיות אחר שבת. amar Rabi Zeira
gezeira mishum Yom Tov shechal lihiyot achar Shabbos. The only reason you
ever have to bring your עירוב anywhere is because of יום טוב
yom tov after שבת. shabbos. What does that mean? If יום טוב
yom tov was on Sunday and I wanted the עירוב to work
for Sunday, I would have to have it there right on, you
know, from Saturday leading into Saturday night. Okay? If I didn't actually
have it physically placed there, right, you could not say that in
theory I could get it there, because I couldn't in theory carry
it on שבת. shabbos If I am putting it there on late
Friday afternoon the שבת shabbos עירוב, then you could say: okay, בין
השמשות bein hashmashos it would only be rabbinic like רבי Rebbi and
maybe I could get it there doing rabbinic violations and so on.
Okay? But if it's right. So that's in theory I could I
could bring it there during בין השמשות bein hashmashos from Friday leading
into שבת shabbos wherever it would be. But I can't in theory
bring it there from שבת shabbos. leading into Sunday. It's actually שבת.
shabbos So there's no way in theory I could have brought it
there. So the only reason, according to this, the only reason you
ever need to physically put your עירוב somewhere is for the case
of שבת shabbos, leading into Sunday where you can't even say in
theory I could have brought it there. But every normal case, a
Friday leading into שבת, shabbos. in principle, if you say in theory,
in principle you could always say you know what בין השמשות bein
hashmashos it's true my עירוב isn't here but in theory I could
get it here because I could it's only a rabbinic problem right
now it's בין השמשות and there's ways rabbinicly to get it here.
Okay? So that is a pretty radical idea that the whole reason
you have to need to have to get it there, have to
actually place it, is just for the case of יום טוב yom
tov following שבת. But in a way of seeing it, it's the
גמרא sort of getting frustrated and the גמרא saying, you know, all
of these things hypothetically you could tip the basket, hypothetically you could
do this and I think it was really brought out by the
earlier cases. If it's even outside of שש אמות shesh amos it
counts because you could get it, so what's the limit? You could
always say in theory I could get it to me. Okay, so
at one degree the גמרא is saying אי הכי נמי, ei hachi
nami, but we'll continue this conversation tomorrow. Enjoy יום טוב yom tov
then. It'll be a basket case. Good line, good line. See you
soon. Enjoy יום טוב yom tov then.